<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition to all such as shall intend hereafter to enter the state of matrimony, godlily and agreeably to lawes set forth by the most reverend father in God, Matthew Arch-bishop of Canterbury ...</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1559-1575 : Parker)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08998</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22459414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22459414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08998)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition to all such as shall intend hereafter to enter the state of matrimony, godlily and agreeably to lawes set forth by the most reverend father in God, Matthew Arch-bishop of Canterbury ...</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1559-1575 : Parker)</author>
                  <author>Parker, Matthew, 1504-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. Okes, for Iohn Harrison, and are to be sold at the signe of the Unicorne in Pater-noster-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in All Soul's College (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage (Canon law) --  Protestant Episcopal.</term>
               <term>Consanguinity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:25563:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Admonition to all ſuch as ſhall intend hereafter to
enter the ſtate of Matrimony, godlily and agreeably to Lawes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, that they contract not with ſuch perſons as be hereafter expreſſed, nor with any of like degree, againſt the law of God, and the lawes of the
Realme.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they make no ſecret contracts, without conſent or counſell of their Parents or Elders, under whoſe authority they be: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to Gods lawes and mans ordinances.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they contract not anew with any other upon divorce and ſeparation made by the Iudge for a time, the Lawes yet ſtanding to
the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Arriage is honourable among all men, and the bed undefiled. But whoremongers and adulterers God will iudge. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>To avoyd fornication let every man have his wife, and let every woman have her husband. He that cannot containe, let him marry: For better
it is to marry, than to burne. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Vnto the married I command, not I, but the Lord; let not the wife depart from her husband. But if ſhe depart, let her remain unmarried, or
he reconcited unto her husband. And let not the Husband put away his <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LEVITIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S. XVIII. &amp; XX.</bibl>
                  <p>None ſhall come neere to any of the kinred of his fleſh to uncover her ſhame: I am the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="tables_of_marriage_laws">
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A Man may not marry his</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus in linea recta aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Avi.</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Grandmother</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Avi relicta.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>grandfathers wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Proſocrus, vel ſocrus magna.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Wives Grandmother</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus, inaequalis, in linea
tranſverſa aſcendente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Amita</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers ſiſter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Matertera</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers ſiſter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Patrui relicta</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers brothers wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Avunculi relicta</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers brothers wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Amita uxoris.</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>Wives fathers ſiſter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Matertera uxoris.</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>Wives mothers ſiſter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus in linea recta aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Mater</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>Mother</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Noverca</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>Stepmother</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Socrus</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>Wives mother</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Filia</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>Daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privigna.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>Wives daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Nurus.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus aequalis in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Soror</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>Siſter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Soror uxoris</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>Wives <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Fratris relicta.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus in linea recta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendente</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex filio</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex filia</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Pronurus. i. relicta nepotis exfilio</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes ſonnes wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Pronurus. i. relicta nepotis ex filia</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters ſonnes wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privigni filia</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>Wives ſonnes daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privignae filia.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>Wives daughters daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus in aequalis in linea tranſverſali deſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex fratre</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex ſorore</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepotis ex fratre relicta</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers ſonnes wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepotis ex ſorore relicta</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters ſonnes wife</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis uxoris ex fratre.</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>Wives brothers daughter</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis uxoris ex ſorore.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>Wives ſiſters daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A woman may not marrie with her</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus in recta linea aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Grandfather</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Avus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Grandmothers husband.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Aviae relictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands grandfather.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Proſocer, vel ſocer magnus.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus inaequalis in linea tranſverſali aſcendente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers brother</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Patruus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers brother</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Avunculus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers ſiſters huſband.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Amitae relictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers ſiſters husband</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Materterae relictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands fathers brother</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Patruus mariti</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>Huſbands mothers brother.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Avunculus mariti.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>Father</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Pater</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>Stepfather</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Vitricus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands father</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Socer.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus in linea recta deſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>Sonne</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Filius</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>Huſbands ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privignus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters huſband</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Gener</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Primus gradus aequalis in linea tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>Brother</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Frater</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands brother</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Le vin</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters huſband.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Sororis r<gap reason="illegible: torn page" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ctus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secundus gradus in linea recta deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepos ex filio</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepos ex filia</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes daughter husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>progener. i. relictus neptis ex filio</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters daughter huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Progener. i. relictus neptis ex filia</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>Huſbands ſonne ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privigni filius</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands daughters ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Privignae filius.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus gradus inaequalis, in lineà tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſali deſcendente.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepos ex fratre</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>Con.</cell>
                     <cell>Nepos ex ſorore</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers daughters huſband</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex fratre relictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters daughters huſband</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Neptis ex ſorore relictus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>Huſbands brothers ſonne</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Liviris filius. i. nepoſ maritiex fratre.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>Hſubands ſiſters ſonne.</cell>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Gloris filius. i. nepos mariti ex ſorore</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>1 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to be noted, that thoſe perſons which be in the direct
line, aſcendant, and deſcendant, cannot marry together, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
they be never ſo farre aſunder in degree.</p>
            <p>2. It is alſo to be noted, that conſanguinity and affinity
(letting and diſſolving Matrimony) is contracted as well
in them and by them, which be of kindred by the one ſide, as in and by them,
which be of kindred by both ſides.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Item,</hi> that by the Lawes, conſanguinity and affinity (letting and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving
Matrimony) is contracted as well by unlawful company of man and
woman, as by unlawful marriage.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Item,</hi> in contracting betwixt perſons doubtful, which be not expreſſed in
this Table, it is moſt ſure, firſt to conſult with men learned in the Lawes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to
underſtand what is lawful, what is honeſt and expedient, before the finiſhing
of their contracts.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>Item,</hi> that no Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, ſhall ſolemnize Matrimony on
of his, or their Cure, or Pariſh Church or Chappel, and ſhall not ſolemnize the
ſame in private houſes nor lawleſſe nor exempt Churches, under the paines
of the Law, forbidding the ſame And that the Curate have the Certificates
when the parties dwell in diverſe places.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Item,</hi> the bands of matrimony ought to be openly denounced in the Church,
by the Miniſter, three ſeveral Sundayes, or feſtival dayes, to the end, that who
will &amp; can alledge any impediment, may be heard, &amp; that ſtay may be made till
further trial, if any exception be made there againſt it upon ſufficient caution.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>Item,</hi> who ſhall maliciouſly object a frivolous impediment againſt a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
matrimony to diſturb the ſame, is ſubject to the paines of the Law.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>Item,</hi> who ſhall preſume to contract in the degrees prohibited, (though he
do it ignorantly) beſides that the fruit of ſuch copulation may be judged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,
is alſo puniſhable at the Ordinaries diſcretion.</p>
            <p>9. <hi>Item,</hi> if any Miniſter ſhall conjoyn any ſuch, or ſhall be preſent at ſuch
contracts making, he ought to be ſuſpended from his Miniſtry for three
yeares: and otherwiſe to be puniſhed according to the lawes.</p>
            <p>10. <hi>Item,</hi> it is further ordained, that no Parſon, Vicar or Curate do preach,
treat or expound of his own voluntary invention, any matter of controverſie in
the Scriptures, if he be under the degree of a Maſter of Art, except he be licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
by his Ordinary thereunto, but only for the inſtruction of the people, read
the Homilies already ſet forth, &amp; ſuch other forme of doctrine as ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
by authority publiſhed: &amp; ſhall not innovate or alter any thing in the Church
or uſe any old Rite or ceremony, which be not ſet forth by publick authority.</p>
            <byline>Set forth by the moſt reverend Father in God, <hi>Matthew</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Primate of <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitane.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>I. Okes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Unicorne in Pater-noſter-row. <hi>Anno</hi> 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
